Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is, I think I
hear a beep. Okay, today's דף Daf is קוף, Kuf, 100.
And we pick up
on דף ס״ז עמוד ב׳, Daf Samech-Zayin Amud Bet, בר מצוה דכולי
עלמא לתתא,
Bar Mitzvah
De-Kulei Alma Le-Tata, and we have, yep, דף ס״ז עמוד ב׳, Daf
Samech-Zayin Amud Bet,
and we are תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan about six lines about eight
lines from the bottom. Everybody's got that? So we are dealing with
these interesting cases about these babies that got mixed up and you
don't know exactly who's who's, you know, who's
whose brother and multiple יבומים Yibums or whatever, multiple חליצות, Chalitzas, etc.
And then the most recent case is כהנים Kohanim getting mixed up
with slaves of
כהנים. Kohanim. The mother and her the mother's child and the child
of her slave got mixed up, so one is a כהן, Kohen,
one is the slave of a כהן, Kohen, and then dealing with
all of the implications. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara now picks up with
the
following: תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. And so part of this was when
the slave and the כהן, Kohen, these two men who you don't
know who is who, go to collect the תרומה, Terumah, can you
give
a slave not in the presence of a כהן? Kohen? On the
one hand it's allowed for him to eat תרומה, Terumah, allowed for
him to bring back to his master. On the other hand, are
we concerned that it'll lead people to believe that he is a
כהן? Kohen? So with that in mind, תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: עשרה
אין חולקים להם תרומה בבית הגרנות. Asarah Ein Chlokim Lahem Terumah Be-Veit
Ha-Gornot. There are ten people who though they are have a right
to תרומה, Terumah, you do not actually distribute to them תרומה Terumah
in the threshing floor. ואלו הן: Ve-Eilu Hen: What?
You do it elsewhere?
Yeah, well we'll see. ואלו הן. Ve-Eilu Hen. You will, that's what
the ברייתא Baraita will spell that out. And these are they: חרש
שוטה וקטן. Cheresh Shoteh Ve-Katan. Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara going to
explain all these because it's not obvious why not. I mean if
you have the חרש, Cheresh, the deaf-mute, the שוטה, Shoteh, the person
out of right mind, the קטן, Katan, if they're כהנים Kohanim they're
allowed to eat תרומה. Terumah. So what should exactly be the problem?
So anyway we'll see. טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. Tumtum Ve-Androgynus. טומטום Tumtum is somebody
who you don't know if it's male or female because his genitalia
is covered up. אנדרוגינוס Androgynus is somebody with both genitalia.
Again what's the problem? If it's a כהן, Kohen, he's a כהן,
Kohen, he or she's a כהן, Kohen, allowed to eat I mean
even the daughter of a כהן Kohen eats תרומה. Terumah. והעבד, Ve-Ha-Eved,
a slave. So that's one at least we discussed because then people
will think he's a כהן. Kohen. והאשה, Ve-Ha-Ishah, and a woman.
והערל והטמא, Ve-He-Arel Ve-Ha-Tamei, כהן Kohen who is uncircumcised, presumably we're assuming
that it's for a good reason, that his family are hemophiliacs, his
brothers have died in ברית מילה. Bris Milah. טמא, Tamei, person who's
currently טמא, Tamei, can't eat תרומה Terumah in that state. ערל Arel
can't eat תרומה Terumah we know. ונושא אשה שאינה הוגנת לו, Ve-Noiseh
Ishah She-Eina Hoganah Lo, or a man who woman this gets is
relevant also you know one of the few הלכות Halachos that remain
also for נשיאת כפים, Nesiat Kapayim, a כהן Kohen married to a
woman he's not allowed to be married to, for example to a
גרושה. Grushah. וכולן, Ve-Khullan, all of these משגרין להם לבתיהם, Meshagrin Lahem
Le-Vateihem, although you don't distribute to them in the threshing house, threshing
floor, you send it to their homes, because again they're entitled to
תרומה Terumah and they're allowed to eat תרומה, Terumah, חוץ מטמא ונושא
אשה שאינה הוגנת לו. Chutz Mi-Tamei Ve-Noiseh Ishah She-Eina Hoganah Lo. Except
for the last two, except for the case of טמא Tamei and
the woman the guy who's married to a woman who shouldn't be
married to him. You can understand the policy reasons for the last
one, although the טמא Tamei is less clear, I mean the guy
will eventually go to the מקוה, Mikvah, why shouldn't he be able
to get תרומה Terumah right now? So let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara says.
Maybe he'll make us טמא.
Tamei. Well maybe. Okay, let's take a look at what the גמרא
Gemara says. בשלמא חרש שוטה וקטן, Bishlama Cheresh Shoteh Ve-Katan, now the
גמרא's Gemara going to get through the whole go through the whole
list.
I get חרש שוטה וקטן. Cheresh Shoteh Ve-Katan. Why do I get
it? לאו בני דעה אינהו. Lav Benei Dei'a Innu. They're not people
of you know mature intellect. So what? I mean, so רש"י Rashi
says: לאו בני דעה אינהו, Lav Benei Dei'a Innu, says רש"י, Rashi,
וזילותא דתרומה לחלק להן בגורן לעין כל. Ve-Ziluta De-Terumah Le-Chalek Lahem Be-Goren
Le-Ein Kol. So it's not respectful for תרומה. Terumah. I mean תרומה's
Terumah something קודש, Kodesh, the גורן Goren is something where everybody sort
of sees who's getting תרומה. Terumah. So it's like גורן Goren doesn't
sound like out in your yeah, I understand.
It's not in the town, it's true, but anyway it's visible. So
it is funny that we're so worried about the sort of you
know impressions that people get. So I agree with you, Michael, that
how many people are really there in the גורן, Goren, right? But
nevertheless it's considered like oh you're not you're not showing תרומה Terumah
the proper like respect and dignity, you're just giving it you know
to a kid or you're giving it to a חרש Cheresh and
שוטה, Shoteh, somebody who maybe in society you know is not respected,
right? People so these are people that are not generally sort of
seen as you know serious members of society. That's a reality without
you know saying it's a good thing or not but that's a
reality, then you know then it's not respectful oh look what you're
doing to your תרומה, Terumah, you're just giving it to these people.
So again it's a bit of a problem you know because you
know maybe you should be correcting society's attitude towards these people as
opposed to how we sort of accommodate that, but nevertheless that's how
רש"י Rashi explains what the issue is. תוספות Tosafot points out another
issue, which is וכולן משגרין להם לבתיהן, Ve-Khullan Meshagrin Lahem Le-Vateihen, which
which is if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, which is what I
would have initially thought, he says: ואם תאמר ולמה משגרין. Ve-Im Tomar
Ve-Lama Meshagrin. שוטה הלא לא ישמרוהו בטהרה. shoteh halo lo yishmeruhu betaharah.
If these people are not totally of their competent mind, then maybe
they won't keep it טהור. tahor. Interesting, he only asks that about
a חרש cheresh and a שוטה. shoteh. He imagines that a קטן
katan would be able to do a better job than that.
And he doesn't mention
an איש ish or אשה isha either. All right, well, fine. All
right, ויש לומר שיש להם אפוטרופא בבתיהן. ve-yesh lomar she-yesh lahem apitropas
bevateihen. Maybe they've got somebody supervising them. So he says מכל מקום,
mi-kol makom, even if they have somebody supervising, אין חולקין להם פן
יבואו לחלוק אפילו אין האפוטרופא. ein cholkin lahem pen yavo lachlok afilu
ein ha-apitropas. But you don't distribute to them in the גרונות, gronot,
even though they've got somebody supervising because maybe they'll come to distribute
without the person who is supervising. So according to תוספות, Tosafot, in
the end of the day, the issue can't be that they won't
watch it,
they won't sort of take proper care of it because then you
wouldn't send it at home. It's got to be although he needs
to address that issue although it's this other thing, and therefore presumably
in the גרונות gronot it's a different concern about presumably he would
agree to רש״י. Rashi. Although it's again not I think black and
white in תוספות, Tosafot, and one wonders whether even in the גרונות,
gronot, the concern is
about the fact that if it leads to cases where there's not
somebody to watch them, is it all somehow
related, there's not somebody supervising them, is it all somehow related to
the issue about their ability
to treat it properly. Okay, so that's חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh
ve-katan, which is the issue at least the way רש״י Rashi says
it about a question of respect. And now we move on.
טומטום ואנדרוגינוס נמי, tumtum ve-androgynos nami, טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס androgynos as
well, בריה בפני עצמו הינהו. biryah bifnei atzmo hinhu. They are their
own creatures. And what does that mean? Meaning they don't fall into
our simple binary gender
binary. And therefore רש״י, Rashi, הוי זילותא דקדשים. havye ziluta de-kodshim. Same
point, people just look at them more like unusual, they don't fall
into the normal sort of categories of our binary gender in society.
So
therefore it's not seen as appropriate for תרומה. terumah. So as I
said, all these things are interesting, right? We're not sort of critiquing
society's way of putting people at the margins, we're more accepting it
and therefore dealing with it. It's an issue that comes up a
lot by קדשים, kodshim, like the whole way the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, right, the כהנים kohanim with מומים mumim are excluded. Everything has
to be aesthetically beautiful and perfect and so on.
What about the whole more idea like כי האדם יראה לעינים וה׳
יראה ללבב? ki ha-adam yireh laeinayim ve-Hashem yireh lalevav? What about an
attitude that קדושה kedushah is supposed to be about the internal quality
of people and not the external? But the problem is that we
live in also a real society where people's understanding of holiness and
God and all these things are impacted by the aesthetics and filtered
through their perceptions and their norms, and therefore to some degree we
accommodate that and we play into that. So it's an
interesting thing to stop and acknowledge the problematics of this but then
also the necessity sometimes of this or the reality of this. Anyway,
so that's חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve-katan and טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. tumtum
ve-androgynos. We get that the way society perceives them, it would not
be seen as respectful to give them תרומה terumah in some type
of a public fashion.
עבד נמי דלמא אתי לאסוקי מתרומה ליוחסין. eved nami dilma ati le-asuki
mi-terumah le-yuchsin. עבד eved is easy because that we discussed; they'll think
that he's a non-עבד eved and they'll marry him off. ערל וטמא,
arel ve-tame, now what about ערל וטמא? arel ve-tame? משום דמאיסי mishum
de-me'isi because these are people that are not allowed to eat תרומה.
terumah. So it's not like זילותא ziluta which is like
degrading or unseemly, this is מאיסי, me'isi, which is it's a different
word but it's like worse. I don't know, disgusting. But anyway, but
somehow it's not somehow that's yeah like putting them in the context
of somebody that can't eat תרומה terumah is seen as also a
type of an abhorrent thing. You don't give it to somebody right
now, it's like a conflict with the whole identity of תרומה, terumah,
handing it over to somebody who can't eat תרומה. terumah.
Although but מאיסי me'isi is some element of disgust though, right? Yeah
so so I still don't understand what the element of disgust is
over here.
Yeah, I mean, it's just the disgusting is, oh, it's disgusting giving
תרומה terumah to somebody who can't eat it. Like, you're putting the
תרומה terumah in the context of
an antithetical type of a context, right? That to me just seems
to be the issue.
Although, then I mean according to רש״י, Rashi, I still don't understand
the difference between זילותא ziluta and מאיסי. me'isi.
Because זילותא ziluta is not antithetical, it's just like it's not respectful.
Here it's like antithetical, like you're giving it over to
somebody who it's like
anyway I think that that's the difference. I'm not sure if it
exactly fits the word מאיסי, me'isi, but at least certainly that is
the reality of the difference. The first set of people are people
that don't have the same standing in society, and these are people
that are at their
essence and is in conflict. תרומה terumah doesn't fit
in their homes, in their context because they can't eat it, yes.
Well, there's a difference between these two categories, and I'm not sure
if it properly explains the difference between the words, but ערל וטמא,
arel ve-tame, nobody necessarily knows. Aha. That they know themselves.
Aha, that's interesting. So you don't have
זילותא.
ziluta.
Right. Interesting. So the זילותא *Zilusa* has to do with an issue
that's societal perception, whereas מיאסי *mi'asi* could be some type of an
objective definition that it's מאוס *ma'os* even if nobody knows about it.
Yeah, Charlie? What's the טבול יום *Tevul Yom*?
Oh, come on. We won't worry about that. I mean, you're saying
because it'll be done by the end of the day? Right.
Yeah, so that might
be different because then it'll naturally go off anyway. So it's not
clear. It doesn't exactly explain the parameters here.
So טבול יום *Tevul Yom* is a שני *sheni*?
Yeah. I mean, he can't touch תרומה terumah *Truma*, but you're right.
It's an interesting point. On the one hand, he can't touch any
תרומה terumah *Truma* right now. On the other hand, it's a very
transient state, so I don't know. It's an interesting question. Okay. So
אשה *Isha*. So we're basically down to the woman, right? So she's
not in some... אשה *Isha*? No, I'm sorry, נושא אשה שאינה הגונה
לו *noseh isha she'eino hogen lo* משום קנסא *mishum knasa*. We're fining
him, right? We don't want to... if we want him to sort
of have some societal sanction against
him, hopefully, A, that we show we don't tolerate that, and B,
to maybe he'll even do something about it.
Why send it to him in his home?
No, except he's one of the guys we don't send to a
home. The only two people we don't send even to their home
are the man married to the woman he's not... he shouldn't, and
the טמא tamei *tamei*. Now אשה *Isha*, so finally the one thing
we don't understand is a woman, right? That's she fits into the
into the standard gender binary.
She's, you know, a person of recognized status within society. So what's
the problem with a woman?
So אשה מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama? לא *Isha mai ta'ama lo*? פליגי
בה רב פפא Rav Pappa ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע *Pligi bah
Rav Pappa ve-Rav Huna breih de-Rav Yehoshua*. חד אמר משום גרושה grusha
*Chad amar mishum grusha*
because if you start giving to a woman who is married to
a כהן kohen *Kohen* or the daughter of a כהן kohen, *Kohen*,
but once you start giving to women, so what'll happen is you'll
give to a woman because she's the wife of a כהן kohen,
*Kohen* and then you'll continue to give to her after she gets
divorced because you're in the habit of giving to her, which is
pretty funny because it assumes that you can't trust the woman herself
to self-, you know, to know to not go once she's no
longer entitled.
Maybe she won't be aware of the הלכה halachah? *halacha*. Maybe she'll
just get habituated to going and collecting תרומה trumah *Truma*. Maybe we're
not actually making her out to be a מזיד *mezid* or a
רשע *rasha*. What?
No, but then you'd give it to a man maybe who's a
נושא אשה שאינה הגונה לו *noseh isha she'eino hogen lo*. I mean,
he would...
yeah, but that's... yeah, but
men... anyway, those are not דאורייתא *De-Oraisa* statuses of disqualification. Once a
woman is divorced, it's a real case of a זר *zar* that's
eating תרומה trumah *Truma*.
What?
Worry about that maybe she'll have a greater need?
Because women don't have, right, need, you know, don't have their own
means of support. That's also true. So okay, so that's one reason.
וחד אמר משום יחוד *Ve-chad amar mishum yichud*. Now you know, like
בועז *Boaz* and רות *Rus*, you know, that let's you know what's
a woman doing in the גורן *goren*, right? So people shouldn't say,
you know, what's she doing? There you go. So anyway, you don't
want to send women over there to the to the threshing floor
where there's nobody else around. Okay.
I think things are kind of public in זילותא *zilusa*.
I know, that is funny because before we said זילותא *zilusa*, now
we're saying יחוד *yichud*. That's absolutely true. And the גמרא gemara, *Gemara*
is going to deal with some of that right now. So let's
take a look. But that's an excellent point. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, מאי בינייהו *mai beinaihu*? What would be a difference between
these two approaches? איכא בינייהו בי דרי *Ika beinaihu bei dari*. בי
דרי *Bei dari* is a threshing floor. בי דרי דמקרב למתא *Bei
dari de-makrav le-mata*, it's close to the city, ולא שכיחי בה אינשי
*ve-lo shchichi bah inshi*, but it's not... but there's not a lot
of traffic. So because it's close to the city, presumably רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says it means that the woman is known in, you know,
is known around
and therefore people will know if she's a גרושה gerushah *grusha* or
not. So if she's on her way to go to this, you
know, to this threshing floor right at the outskirts of the city,
word will get around and therefore nothing's going to happen. People will
know
that she's divorced and people are aware of it and nobody's going
to give it to
her incorrectly because you know people are aware enough close to the
city. But the reality is in the actual location itself, it's pretty
secluded and pretty private. Okay, so it's enough that they're part of
the grapevine but not enough that people are actually present. So there
still would be a יחוד *yichud* concern. אי נמי *Ei nami*, or
the reverse, דמרחק *de-merchak*, it's distant from the city, so people don't
know, you know, what her status is and they don't know that
she's a גרושה gerusha, *grusha*, but ושכיחי בה אינשי *ve-shchichi bah inshi*,
and there but there's a lot of traffic there, so there's no
concern of יחוד *yichud*. Okay. וכולן משגרין להן לבתיהן *Ve-kulan meshagrin lahen
le-vateihen*. All of them you send it to them to their homes,
חוץ מטמא mitamei. ונושא אשה שאינה הגונה לו *chutz mi-tamei ve-noseh isha
she'eino hogen lo*. Okay, so נושא אשה שאינה הגונה לו *noseh isha
she'eino hogen lo* we understand, that's a case of a, like, you
know, communal sanction. But what's the issue about the טמא tamei *tamei*?
And how's that different, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, than ערל *arel*?
אבל ערל משגרין לו *Aval arel meshagrin lo*, but the ערל *arel*
you would send. Right, now obviously the ערל *arel* isn't going to
eat. What's the ערל *arel* going to do with it? He'll feed
it to his wife, to his slaves, to his children. So a
טמא tamei *tamei* also, טמא tamei *tamei* is even better. Besides that
he could feed it to his wife and slaves and children, he
could just when it's time to go to the מקוה *mikvah* eat
it himself. So why do you not send it to the טמא
tamei *tamei* and you send it to the
ערל *arel*? So מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*? Why do you send... to
the
ערל *arel*, משום דאנוס *mishum de-anus*, because it's out of his control.
Presumably if a guy is an ערל *arel*, it's caused by he's
a hemophiliac and he has no choice. So why should you fine
him? Why shouldn't you send it to him? And again, it's not
appropriate to do it in public. You don't do it in the
threshing floor but why not send to his home and he'll give
it to the people that are allowed to eat it? So okay,
so that's what you do by the ערל *arel*. So טמא tamei
*tamei* נמי *nami*, if that's what you do by the ערל *arel*,
so say do this by the טמא tamei *tamei* also. You know,
people become טמא *tamei* due to no fault of their own and
why not, so you don't want to do it in public fine,
but why not send it to his house? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says no, הא אניס האי? טמא נמי הא אניס? *Ha anis
hai? Tamei nami ha anis?* But it says no, האי נפיש אונסיה
והאי לא נפיש אונסיה *Hai nafush unsei ve-hai lo nafush unsei*. One
of them, the degree of like out of your control is yeah,
exactly, is completely out of your control. If a guy is a
hemophiliac, he's got a medical condition, there's absolutely nothing he can do
about it. Whereas the case by the טמא *tamei* we want there
to be a little bit presumably a little bit of societal sanction,
a little bit of like okay work harder, you know? Yes, we
know sometimes it's out of your control, sometimes a person actually it's
a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to be טמא *tamei*. He went and he
buried a relative, he buried his father or something like that. But
nevertheless as a general point of underscoring how important it is for
כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim* to be zealous about remaining טהור *tahor*,
we want there to be a little bit of a sanction, you
know, in that case as well. Okay? Not necessarily that every case
there's something he could have done about it, but just as a
little bit of a point about like we don't want, you know,
we want to say we're bothered about the fact that you're טמא
*tamei*.
Okay? So much so you're not even sending it to their house.
What?
So much yeah that you're not even sending it to their house.
Which again is quite funny, like the guy, you know, might be
able to go to the מקוה *mikvah* today and you're not sending
it to his house. So anyway. Okay, תנו רבנן *Tnu Rabanan*. העבד
והאשה אין חולקין להם תרומה trumah בבית הגרנות *Ha-eved ve-ha-isha ein cholkin
lahem trumah be-veit ha-granot*. The slave and the woman you don't distribute
to them תרומה *trumah* in the threshing floor. So again we discussed,
the slave because people will think that he's a free כהן kohen
*Kohen* and the woman because of various issues, ייחוד yichud *yichud*, גרושה
grusha *grushah*, etc. ובמקום שחולקין *U-ve-makom she-cholkin*,
but in a place where you do distribute to them in the
threshing floor, נותנין לאשה תחילה ופוטרין אותם מיד *nosnin la-isha techila u-potrin
otam mi-yad*. You give it to the woman first, she comes first
of the line and then you send her off to home. You
don't have you don't make her wait around. So minute, מאי קאמר?
*mai kama* minute, מאי קאמר? *mai kama*, what are you saying? First
you say you don't give it and then you say but if
you're giving it give her first. So are you giving her or
you not giving it to her? הכי קאמר *Hachi kamar*, this is
what it means. במקום שחולקין מעשר עני ma'aser ani *Be-makom she-cholkin ma'aser
ani*, meaning no תרומה *trumah* you never give to a woman in
the threshing floor, you send it to the home. But there are
other scenarios where you give to women in the threshing floor. What
are those scenarios? מעשר עני ma'aser ani *Ma'aser ani*. Okay, מעשר עני
ma'aser ani *ma'aser ani*, women are also if they're if they're עניים
aniyim *aniyim*, they're entitled to מעשר עני ani *ma'aser ani* every third
and sixth year. That you would give to the woman. Now why
is it different? If there's a ייחוד yichud, *yichud* concern or well
there's not a גרושה grusha *grushah* concern, that's easy, right? If the
issue is גרושה grusha, *grushah*, right? So that's only a concern by
תרומה *trumah* and כהן kohen *Kohen*. By מעשר עני *ma'aser ani*, if
a woman's an עניה *aniya*, it doesn't she's always entitled to it,
right? But if it's a ייחוד yichud *yichud* concern, it's not exactly
clear why you're more you're more prepared to give מעשר עני *ma'aser
ani* than than תרומה *trumah*. Can you can you guess why you
might be why less of a concern giving מעשר עני *ma'aser ani*
than תרומה *trumah* for it's a ייחוד *yichud* concern?
I think that there are a lot of more of a crowd
of people. First of all תרומה *trumah*'s a very small amount, what
is it, 2%, so you're pretty much done with giving the תרומה
*trumah* pretty quickly, right? And whereas by מעשר *ma'aser* there's a lot
of עניים aniyim *aniyim*, לא יחדל אביון *lo yechdal evyon*, so that's
number one what you would imagine. So certainly there's no גרושה grusha,
*grushah* concern, no ייחוד *yichud* concern. רש"י *Rashi* also adds another fascinating
point and תוספות Tosafos. *Tosafos* elaborates on it. If you take a
look at רש"י *Rashi*, רש"י *Rashi* says the following... הכי קאמר
*hachi kamar*, it's about six lines from the narrow line, top of
the narrow line. אמר הכי קאמר דבמקום שחולקין לאו אתרומה קאי והכי
קאמר ודווקא שחולקין נמי לנשים *Amar hachi kamar, de-makom she-cholkin lav a-trumah
ka'i ve-hachi kamar, ve-davka she-cholkin nami le-nashim*. Something you do distribute to
women. כגון מעשר עני שהוא מתחלק בתוך הבית בעיר *Kegon ma'aser ani
she-hu mitchalek be-toch ha-bayit ba-ir*, it is not distributed in the threshing
floor, it is distributed in the house. ואין כאן משום ייחוד *Ve-ein
kan mishum yichud*. Now why is it distributed- דשכיחי אינשי *de-shchichi inshi*.
Because there's a lot of people, not just because there's a lot
of demand for it, but also because it's in the city, it's
not out in the field. נותנין לאשה תחילה משום דזילא *Nosnin la-isha
techila mishum de-zila* now because you are going to give a woman,
there's no ייחוד *yichud* concern, there's no גרושה grusha. *grushah* concern, once
you're already giving a woman, you give her first, you don't make
her standing around with all these men. דזילא בה מילתא למיקמא *De-zila
ba miltha le-meikama*, it's not appropriate for her to be standing there
and waiting or whatever, you know again צניעות *tzniut* concerns, other concerns,
you want to take care of the woman first, give it to
her and send her off. And then רש"י *Rashi* explains, מעשר עני
אין מתחלק בגורן אלא בתוך הבית *ma'aser ani ein mitchalek be-goren ela
be-toch ha-bayit* כדכתיב לגר ליתום ולאלמנה *kedichtiv lager layatom ule-almanah*. Okay now
that doesn't exactly show you how it's בתוך הבית *be-toch ha-bayit* because
the לגר ליתום ולאלמנה *lager layatom ule-almanah*, so the ב"ח *Bach* switches
it to ואכלו בשעריך ושבעו
*ve-achlu vish'arecha ve-save'u*. In your gates means in your cities, right? In
your gates is not out in the fields, in your gates is
in the city, in the city. ועוד משום דלא ליכספו עניים *Ve-od
mishum de-lo lichtsfu aniyim*. And the other reason is the עניים *aniyim*
shouldn't be embarrassed. I don't exactly get that, why are the
עניים *aniyim* embarrassed. If anything, they're less embarrassed, right? It's outside of
the city, fewer people see them. So I don't exactly get רש"י'ס
claim that עניים are less embarrassed if you distribute it in the
city than out of the city. Maybe it means that you're not
מטריח matriach the עניים to schlepp out of the city, but I
don't exactly get לא ליכספו עניים. lo lichsefu aniyim. Maybe you can
figure that out. Anyway, so that's fascinating, that you distribute the מעשר
עני in the city. I mean, right? I think most people aren't
aware of that. You assume you're in your threshing floor, you distribute
all the מעשרות. ma'asrot. But no, you distribute your תרומה out there
in the field, and then you bring your מעשר עני into the
city and you distribute it there. Okay, so the woman, therefore you
would give it to the woman, not a ייחוד problem, not a
גירוש geirush problem. But if you're giving it to her,
it's not appropriate to make her be waiting around with that whole
throng of men, so therefore you give it to her first. Let's
just finish this top two dots and then I'll take the questions.
Okay, so במקום שמחלק מעשר עני נותנים לאשה תחילה מה טעמא משום
זילותא.
B'makom she'mechallek ma'aser ani notnim l'isha techila mah ta'ama
mishum ziluta. אמר רבא מריש כי הוו אתו גברא ואיתתא לדינא, Amar
Rava merish ki havu atu gavra v'itata l'dina, initially when a man
and woman would come before me for a court case, קמאי kamai
in front of me, הוי שרינא תיגרא דגברא ברישא, hava sharina tigra
d'gavra b'reisha, first I would literally undo the conflict of the man
first, meaning I would attend to the man's court case first. אמינא,
amina, why did I go, why did I give priority to the
man? I would say דמיחייב במצוות demichayeiv b'mitzvot because he's of greater,
you know, religious status, he's obligated in מצוות. mitzvot. Okay, so this—these
are places where we really should
have Rifka in the שיעור, shiur, we really mourn her absence.
These גמרות. gemarot. Anyway, so here's the גמרא, Gemara, you know, unapologetically,
right? Yeah, men are of a higher status, I would deal with
the man first. כיון דשמענא לה להא, Keivan d'shamana lah l'ha, since
I heard this issue about first distributing the מעשר עני to the
women, so שרינא תיגרא דאיתתא ברישא. sharina tigra d'itata b'reisha. First I
deal with the woman's case first. מה טעמא משום זילותא, Mah ta'ama
mishum ziluta, because it's disrespect, you know, it's not seemly
for her to be standing and waiting for her case to be
heard. Again, men are more—you know, it's more acceptable socially and men
are more accustomed to being in public and to being in these
sort of, you know, in these settings. And therefore,
you could argue whether on a societal level unseemly or for the
woman unseemly, it's difficult for everybody in these types of settings when
those are your norms of society. So therefore, you deal with the
woman's case and then let her go home. So again, quite fascinating
in terms of reflecting about the reality of woman's status in society,
like the other discussions we had about the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh v'katan and the טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. tumtum v'androgynous. No feeling of a
need to do something about those societal realities, but how do you
attend to those realities once those are actually
what they are. Yes, now there were some questions.
Michael. You said before about the גרושה grusha versus ייחוד, you know,
same thing can be she comes with her kids, right?
Right, that's a good point, like would you judge each case individually
or not? Like if there happened to be a lot of people
today, would it be allowed? Presumably, you would make some try to
make some more general, you know, some more clear rules rather than
assess every case by case scenario, right? It's always a question. Yeah.
But doesn't this imply that in the end of the day, the
sensibility about the social discomfort of women trumps the obligation to do
מצוות? mitzvot? If you have to do an order, like who's going
to come first, right?
In other words, the question—it's not trumping the obligation to do מצוות,
mitzvot, it's a question about the man's status in society as opposed
to—but you know, it's sort of
like—right, I mean, you know, it's sort of like the whole case
about, you know,
that people have greater status in society. So an עני and an
עשיר ashir come to you in דין, din, right? The עשיר ashir
is the one that has greater status in society, but you know,
but the right, but you know, it's look, it's consistent with the
Torah's general approach, which is greater sensitivity to those that are more
marginal and need more protection than to those that have the greater
status within society. Right, that's exactly, yes.
If an owner forgot to leave פאה pe'ah and accidentally or deliberately
harvested, he's required to leave it in a pile later, and women
come to get out in the field.
Out in the field, right.
I don't remember about whether I would presume they would be able
to come to the granaries as well, and if it's not given
to them, they just take it.
Right. Yeah, but I don't know. I think out in the field
is less of these ייחוד issues than the other one. But I
don't know. It's a good question. Okay. הגדילו התערובות. Higdilu ha-ta'aruvot. Let's
keep people moving. Now this mixture, this you know, man and these
two men, one is a כהן kohen and one is the slave
of a כהן, kohen grow up. If they free one another, then
they can get married, but then there's still these issues of תרומה
etc. Okay. שחררו. shichreru. So the משנה mishnah says they did, meaning
if they freed one another. אי בעי האי ואי בעי האי. i
ba'ei hai v'i ba'ei hai. The משנה mishnah means if they want
to, they can free one another. ואמאי לישא שפחה אינו יכול בת
חורין אינו יכול. v'amai lissa shifcha eino yachol bat chorin eino yachol.
Why are they allowed to choose? Right now neither of them can
get married because each one is a ספק כהן ספק עבד safek
kohen safek eved and therefore you can't. You can't marry a slave
woman because you might be a כהן, kohen. you can't marry an
עבד eved because you might be, you can't marry a free woman
because you might be an עבד, eved, so they should be obligated
to free one another. We know other places we force a master
to free a slave in this situation because we can't, we won't
tolerate that situation. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אימא כופין אותן ומשחררין
זה את זה, eima kofin osan u-mishachrin zeh es zeh, fine, read
that into the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah doesn't say if they
choose to free one another, it means that you insist that they
free one another. Again, you know, they make a תנאי, t'nai, whichever
one is the כהן kohen, is freeing the other one who's the
slave. Okay. נותנין להם חומרי כהנים וחומרי ישראל. Nosnin lahem chumrei kohanim
v'chumrei Yisrael. So if and these, now after going through all the
נפקא מינות, nafka minas, we say we treat them with the stringency
of a כהן kohen and stringency of a ישראל. Yisrael. So what's
left that we haven't identified? So the גמרא Gemara, says, למאי הלכתא,
l'mai hilchasa, so what's, for what הלכה? halachah אמר פפא, Amar Pappa,
למנחתם נקמצת כמנחת ישראל ואינן נאכלת כמנחת כהנים. l'minchasam nikmetzes k'minchas Yisrael,
v'einan ne'echeles k'minchas kohanim.
Okay,
when a ישראל Yisrael brings a מנחה, minchah, you have to take
the, take the handbreadth, the כהן kohen takes the handbreadth, it's like
the שחיטה sh'chitah of a קרבן, korban, and puts it, burns it
on the altar like the throwing of the blood of the קרבן
korban on the altar. If a כהן kohen brings a מנחה, minchah,
it says that וכל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה לא תאכל. v'chol minchas
kohen kalil tihyeh, lo te'achel. It has to be fully burned. There's
no קמיצה. k'mitzah. Okay, so what do you do if this guy
is a ספק כהן ספק ישראל, safek kohen safek Yisrael, and he
brings a מנחה? minchah? What do you do with it? Do you
take the קמיצה k'mitzah and not burn the rest? Then you're not
treating it like the מנחה minchah of a כהן. kohein Do you
burn the whole thing? So is that okay? Can you do by
מנחת ישראל, minchas Yisrael, do the קמיצה k'mitzah and then burn the
rest of it? Let's take a look. What you really do is
you pay him to bring and you give him money for a
sheep or something so you don't have to deal with it. Okay,
but anyway, כמנחת כהנים. k'minchas kohanim. So what do you do? How
do you both do the מנחה minchah and not eat it? So
הא כיצד, ha keitzad, how do you do with it? הקומץ קרב
בפני עצמו, Hakometz kareiv bifnei atzmo, first you do the קמיצה k'mitzah
and you burn that. והשיריים, V'hashiyarayim, and then the rest of it,
קריבין בפני עצמן, kreivin bifnei atzman, you burn that separately, but you
burn on the altar, but you burn both of them, but not
as one unit. So if it's a מנחת ישראל minchas Yisrael and
you did the קמיצה k'mitzah and then you just chose to burn
the rest rather than eat it, okay, which you could ask how
you're allowed to burn קדשים kodshim that have to be eaten, but
all right, I mean you don't have much of a choice. And
if it's a מנחת כהן, minchas kohen, you burn the whole thing.
So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, you're not allowed to do
that. איקרי כאן כל שממנו לאישים הרי הוא בבל תקטירון. Ikri kan
kol she-mimenu l'ishim, harei hu b'val taktirun.
It says you're not allowed to burn לא תקטירו ממנו אשה להשם
ועל המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח. lo saktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem v'al
hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu l'reiach nichoach.
It speaks of certain things like כל שאור וכל דבש, kol se'or
v'chol d'vash, right, certain sweet things, whatever, yeast and honey, etc., you
cannot burn on the altar. But the דרשה d'rashah that חזל Chazal
reach from it is, not just לא תקטירו ממנו, lo saktiru mimenu,
don't burn from this on the altar, don't offer from this, but
לא תקטירו ממנו, lo saktiru mimenu, anything that you have offered a
piece of it on the altar, the part that doesn't go on
the altar, like the meat of a קרבן korban that's not an
עולה, olah, or the remainder of a מנחה, minchah, any, the part
that's not on the altar is prohibited to burn on the altar.
So how are you allowed to burn the remnant of this מנחה
minchah on the altar? כל שממנו אשה, Kol she-mimenu isheh, anything that's
from it went on the fire, הרי הוא, harei hu, the stuff
that's left behind is בבל תקטירון, b'val taktirun, cannot be burned, cannot
be offered. So how are you allowed to burn the rest? אמר
רב יהודה בריה דרבי שמעון בן פזי, Amar Rav Yehuda breih d'Rabbi
Shimon ben Pazi, דמסיק להו לשם עצים. d'masik leihu l'shem eitzim. All
right, you burn it on the altar, but you, what you say
is if this is a מנחת ישראל minchas Yisrael and not a
מנחת כהן, minchas kohen, I'm not putting it on the altar as
a form of an offering, I'm just dumping it on the altar
as a type of a fuel. Okay, so somehow by making that
stipulation that redefines the nature of what the putting it on the
altar meant, and therefore you did not transgress. Of course, the funny
thing is, is that, is that that's one thing if you are
con, are you like absolutely saying here's what it's about, it's about
fuel, not about a קרבן. korban. You're actually not certain if it's
the מנחה minchah of a כהן, kohein you do want it to
be put on as a קרבן. korban. So you're defining what it
is you're doing, you know, it's like בתנאי. b'tnai. And in case
it happens to be the מנחת ישראל, minchas Yisrael, I'm just putting
it on as fuel.
You know, it's a great example of how כוונות kavanos helps define
what it is on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Exactly. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara. says, הניחא לרבי אליעזר, ha
nicha l'Rabbi Eliezer, that's good according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, there's
this debate in the גמרא, Gemara in another גמרא, Gemara's about exactly
this, that you don't know what to do with the limbs of
an, of a sacrifice. Was it a חטאת? chattas? Was it an
עולה? olah? And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, well just put it
on the altar and say, you know, if it's a חטאת chattas
and doesn't go on the altar, we're going to treat it as
if it's just fuel. But the Rabbis disagree. So that works for
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
But לרבנן מאי איכא למימר, l'rabanan mai ika l'meimar, the Rabbis don't
accept that you can just say, oh this is what, it's only
going up as fuel. Okay, so here's the other thing.
עביד ליה כרבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון, Avid lei k'Rabbi Eliezer ben Rabbi
Shimon, which is a case about a,
there's a whole question about when a כהן kohein, brings a, there's
some type of a מנחה minchah that's a חטאת, chattas, like a,
you know, case of עולה ויורד oleh v'yored etc. by, by טומאה,
tumah, and if a כהן kohein. brings a חטאת מנחה, chattas minchah,
a מנחה minchah that's brought for חטא, cheit, does it follow the
same הלכה halachah that it's all burned, or is it just that
the קמיצה's k'mitzah burned? Okay, there's a question in this הלכה that
the מנחה minchah of a כהן kohein is all burned. What do
you do when it's a מנחת חוטא? minchas chotei? So therefore, רבי
אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer ben Rabbi Shimon says that, he's not
certain and therefore what he says is, let's take a look.
So the rabbis say you do like we're suggesting here. First you
do the קומץ kometz by itself and the rest separate. And רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon says no, the שיריים shyrayim
aren't burnt. You do a קומץ, kometz, you don't burn the שיריים
shyrayim in this case of a כהן kohein bringing a מנחת חוטא,
minchas chotei, okay, because because it's not fully burnt. And on the
other hand, you don't eat the remainder. So what do you do
if you're not going to burn it on the altar and you're
not going to eat it? So let's take a look. רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon אומר, omer, הקומץ קרב לעצמו hakometz
kareiv l'atzmo
in this case of a כהן Kohen. bringing a מנחת חוטא, minchas
chotei, you bring the קומץ, kometz, it's not like a normal מנחה
mincha of a כהן, Kohen you don't burn the whole thing, you
bring the קומץ. kometz. On the other hand, you're not allowed to
eat the remainder. So it's exactly our case. So what do you
do with the remainder? והשיריים מתפזרין על בית הדשן. v'hashyrayim mispazrin al
beis hadeshen.
Fine. So this is the obvious solution. What would you say? You
would say on the one hand you're not allowed to eat it,
on the other hand you don't burn it on the altar. So
what do you do with it? You burn it off of the
altar, you burn it with the pile of ashes what you do
with פסול קרבנות. pasul korbanos. ואפילו רבנן לא פליגי עליה דרבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון v'afilu rabanan lo paligi alei d'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon אלא
במנחת חוטא של כהנים. ela b'minchas chotei shel kohanim.
They only debate with him in terms of the particulars of what
is the תורה Torah prescribing for the מנחת חוטא, minchas chotei, a
מנחת חטאת minchas chatas for a כהן. Kohen דבת הקרבה היא, d'bas
hakrava hi, the rabbis actually think that you burn the whole thing,
that you offer the whole thing on the altar. אבל הכא, aval
hacha, but if you really are stuck that you know on the
one hand you have to do a קומץ kometz and on the
other hand you're not allowed to eat the rest because you might
be a כהן Kohen. and not a ישראל, Yisrael, so what do
you do? In that case where you really don't know what to
do and you're not allowed to eat the rest because if you're
a כהן Kohen. you're not allowed to eat the remainder, in that
case אפילו רבנן מודו afilu rabanan modu they would agree that what
you do with the rest is that you burn it in the
pile of ashes what you do with פסול קרבנות. pasul korbanos. So
that was a little jump to קדשים Kodshim because we were way
too deep in יבמות, Yevamos, so that's just a key to keep
you on your toes.
All right, now remind us where's the physically the בית הדשן? Beis
Hadeshen?
It's at the it's at the side of the ramp going up
to the altar. Question whether it's on which side of the ramp
it is, the east or the west, there's a whole discussion רש"י
תוספות. Okay. מי שלא שהתה אחר בעלה שלושה חודשים. Mi shelo shahasa
achar ba'ala shlosha chodashim. Okay,
so now again we're in the פרשה parsha of not knowing people's
exact identity. So here's another case. Okay, you don't know who the
father is. A woman did not wait after her husband had been
let's say dead,
reported died or maybe divorced her, not just reported it, had died
or divorced her. She didn't wait to remarry three months. So therefore
and then she got pregnant, you know, very soon after she married
the second guy. So you don't know is it the second guy's
child or the first guy's
child. ונישאת וילדה ואין ידוע בין תשעה לראשון v'nisais v'yalda v'ein yadu'a
ben tesha larishon was born after six months after marrying the second
guy. You don't know if it's a nine months child from her
first husband אם בן שבע לאחרון im ben sheva leacharon or a
seven months child from the second husband. Okay, so you just don't
know who the father is. היו לה בנים מן הראשון ובנים מן
השני. Hayu la banim min harishon ubanim min hasheni. Now let's say
she also had definite children beforehand and after. So this woman has
had children from husband number one, children from husband number two, and
this guy falls right in the middle. You don't know if his
father is father number one or father number two. Everybody gets the
scenario? All right fine. So חולצין ולא מייבמין. Choltzin v'lo meyabmin. And
then he marries a woman and dies. So what do the brothers
do? So one of these sets of brothers has to do חליצה
chalitza or ייבום, yibum, right? You just don't know which one. Everybody
here with me? So what do they do? So both sets of
brothers have to do חליצה chalitza because you have to make sure
that the right brother is doing חליצה. chalitza. Now why can't one
set of brothers do חליצה chalitza and the other do ייבום yibum
like we sort of said before? One does חליצה chalitza to his
wife, what?
If it's the wrong one.
So what? So then it's ייבום. yibum. Or let's say it's not
the wrong one. So why not? So then why can't it just
be like some man doing חליצה chalitza to this to this woman?
Right? What's the case?
Here's guy number one.
I got a new marker. Here's the woman, here's guy number two.
So here they've got a
kid, and here was husband number two they've got a kid, and
then somewhere here there's a kid you don't know his identity.
Okay, so and he goes ahead, right, and he marries a woman
and then he dies. Okay, so one of these is the father's
brother. One of these is the father's brother, you don't know which
one, each one has to do חליצה. chalitza. Now why can't this
guy do חליצה, chalitza, let's say, and this guy do ייבום? yibum?
And then this guy will say, look, if I'm the father's brother,
I'm doing a מצוה of ייבום. yibum. If I'm not the father's
brother, then he did חליצה, chalitza, she's מותרת לשוק muteres lashuk and
now I'm and now I'm then he's the father's brother, right, if
I'm not, then he is, he did חליצה, chalitza, she's מותרת לשוק
muteres lashuk and now I'm just going to marry her. Can you
see why not? Why is he not allowed to?
Okay, so do it before, let
him let one do חליצה chalitza and the other do ייבום. yibum.
That was a scenario we had before.
He does חליצה, chalitza, if she's the father's brother it's ייבום, yibum,
if he's not the father's brother then the father's brother did חליצה
chalitza and he'll just marry her.
Because no, because if he's not the father's brother but what if
fine so he's the maternal brother, if he's the maternal brother. If
he's a strange man, it's okay, marry the woman after one guy,
you know, but the point is, if he's not the father's brother,
but he's still the mother's brother, right? So therefore it's עריות. arayos.
Okay, so that's why he can't, right, is that clear? Yes. So
both of them are the mother's brother, and therefore, if you don't
know for certain that you're also the father's brother, you can't do
יבום. yibum. Okay? So therefore they both have to do חליצה. chalitza.
How are they the mother's brother?
Because, because this woman had all three kids.
I mean, I meant a maternal brother, a brother through the mother's
side, okay? So therefore, none of them can marry his wife unless
they know they're also a paternal brother. And since neither one knows
that they're a paternal brother, they both have to do חליצה. chalitza.
It's only the paternity that allows him to...
right, exactly. Okay, unless they're converts. Okay, fine. חולץ ולא מייבם וכן
הוא להם חולץ ולא מייבם. choleitz v'lo meyabem v'chein hu lahem choleitz
v'lo meyabem.
Similarly,
if one of them dies, okay, if one of them dies, okay,
now this guy definitely does not do יבום yibum to this guy's
wife, right? Cause they have different fathers. How about him? So what
does he do to this guy's wife? So he might be a
paternal brother, so he does חליצה. chalitza. Why can't he do יבום?
yibum? Same reason: he might not be, and he is a maternal
brother, and therefore he can't do יבום. yibum. So he can only
do חליצה chalitza and not יבום. yibum. Okay. היו לו אחים מן
הראשון ואחים מן השני שלא מאותה האם. hayu lo achim min harishon
v'achim min hasheini shelo me'osah ha'eim.
So let's say he had brothers from the first and the second
one, not from the same mother. Just one minute, let me just
check Rashi. Rashi and all this...
Okay,
right. So
he,
this guy here, husband number one, okay,
with a different woman has a child, and guy number two with
a different woman has a child, okay? So let's just worry about
one of them, this guy here. Okay, so
what's his relation to this guy here? This guy here is maybe
a, maybe a paternal brother, right? If number one was his father,
then this guy's a paternal brother. Everybody with me? But he is
not, definitely not a maternal brother because the mother was a different
woman, right? So in that case, in that case, he could definitely
marry this woman, right? Is it יבום? yibum? If he's a paternal
brother, he did יבום. yibum. If he's not a paternal brother, then
after she's gotten חליצה, chalitza, well, not actually got a חליצה, chalitza,
let's say the case is that there's no other paternal brothers, okay,
so therefore he would be, if there's nobody here, okay,
so then and then whatever, here we go, he dies. Okay, so
if he's a paternal brother, he does יבום. yibum. If he's not
a paternal brother, then he's definitely not a maternal brother, there are
no other brothers around, she doesn't require יבום yibum or חליצה, chalitza,
so he just marries her.
Okay?
So what do they call that?
Well, they call it a ספק יבום, safek yibum, but I mean...
היו לו אחים מן הראשון ואחים מן השני שלא מאותה האם, hayu
lo achim min harishon v'achim min hasheini shelo me'osah ha'eim,
if there's and no other brothers, it's important to stress, הוא חולץ
ומייבם. hu choleitz umeyabem.
He can do חליצה chalitza or יבום. yibum. Okay? והן אחד חולץ
ואחד מייבם. v'hein echad choleitz v'echad meyabem.
So now, meaning the 'they' is these extra brothers, okay? So let's
say
same scenario, other father, he's the one who dies. Okay, so what
do they do with this wife? So maybe it's a paternal brother,
maybe it's an unrelated woman, right? So what are you going to
do? So same story, one of them can actually choose to do
יבום yibum in this case. But first one has to do חליצה.
chalitza. Because in case it's an unrelated woman, okay, if you're not
a paternal brother here, then this guy is a paternal brother. So
this guy's got to do חליצה chalitza and then you can marry
her as a, just a סתם stam woman. Right, is that clear?
Here's a case where the woman, she's got one of these is
her
brother-in-law. Yes? So
one of them is her brother-in-law, so she needs to get either
יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza from her brother-in-law. So one guy does
חליצה chalitza and one guy can do יבום. yibum. So if this
guy was the brother-in-law, she's free and this guy she's unrelated to,
so she married him. And if this guy wasn't the brother-in-law, then
the חליצה chalitza was meaningless and then this guy she did יבום
yibum with.
Okay. So it's all basically variations of types of scenarios we had
before.
היו אחד ישראל ואחד כהן, hayu echad Yisrael ve-echad Kohen, נושא אשה
ראויה לכהן, nosei ishah re-uyah le-kohen, ואינו מטמא. ve-eino mitamei.
Now, let's say, so that was the יבום וחליצה yibum ve-chalitzah case.
Back to not knowing who your father is. Okay. So he doesn't
know who his father is. Now, this guy was a ישראל. Yisrael.
Well, let's make it easier, that her first husband was a כהן.
Kohen. Okay. So he doesn't know if he's a ישראל Yisrael or
a כהן Kohen. because he doesn't know who his father is. היו
אחד ישראל ואחד כהן, hayu echad Yisrael ve-echad Kohen, נושא אשה ראויה
לכהן. nosei ishah re-uyah le-kohen. Okay,
so he has to marry a woman who's fit for a כהן
Kohen. because he might be a כהן. Kohen That's very similar to
the previous
משנה. mishnah. ואינו מטמא למתים, ve-eino mitamei le-meitim, he can't become טמא
because he might be a כהן. Kohen, ואם נטמא אינו סופג את
הארבעים, ve-im nitma eino sofeg et ha-arba'im, if he did become טמא
he doesn't get lashes because he might not be a כהן. Kohen.
אינו אוכל בתרומה, eino ochel bi-trumah, can't eat תרומה because he might
not be a כהן. Kohen ואם אכל אינו משלם קרן וחומש, ve-im
achal eino meshalem keren ve-chomesh, but if he did he doesn't pay
the fine because he might be a כהן. Kohen, ואינו חולק על
הגורן, ve-eino cholek al ha-goren, and you don't give him תרומה in
the threshing floor. ומוכר תרומתו, ve-mocher trumato,
his own תרומה that he separates,
he, דמי ממונו, demei mamono, owns it because you can't prove he's
not a כהן Kohen but he's not allowed to eat it. So
what does he do if he owns it and he doesn't eat
it? He sells it. והדמים שלו, ve-ha-damim shelo, he keeps the money.
ואינו חולק בקדשי קדשים, ve-eino cholek be-kodshei kodashim, he doesn't get a
portion in קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim because he's obviously not a כהן,
Kohen might not be a כהן. Kohen. ואין נותנים לו את הקדשים,
ve-ein notnim lo et ha-kodashim, you don't give him קדשים kodashim which
for now we'll say means the בכור. bechor. ואין מוציאים את שלו
מידו, ve-ein motzi-in et shelo mi-yado, but you don't take the בכור
bechor out of his hands, again we'll read it like a בכור
bechor because he might be a כהן Kohen but he can't eat
it, he has to wait until it gets a מום mum which
we'll get to. ופטור מן הזרוע והלחיים והקיבה, u-patur min ha-zero'a ve-ha-lechayayim
ve-ha-keivah, if he slaughters an animal he doesn't have to give the
gift to the כהן, Kohen, those, and he can eat them because
those aren't קדשים. kodashim. ובכורו, u-bechoro,
and if he has a בכור, bechor, יהא רועה עד שיסתאב, ye-hei
ro'eh ad she-yista'ev, it grazes until it gets a blemish. ונותנים לו
חומרי כהנים וחומרי ישראלים, ve-notnim lo chumrei kohanim ve-chumrei Yisra-elim, same story
with what the גמרא Gemara said meant a case of a מנחה.
minchah. Okay. היו שניהם כהנים. hayu sheneihem kohanim.
Now both of them are כהנים. kohanim, Now of course if both
of them are what?
Question real quick. Yeah.
Suppose it's about Meron in Israel. So this blow up. Would he
have gotten the inheritance of the land?
So we'll deal right. So no. And we'll get to inheritance in
the
גמרא. Gemara Inheritance like המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, ha-motzi me-chavero alav ha-ra'ayah,
he can't prove that he's entitled. Each side of the family says
you're not our brother. So he's really stuck with that. Now if
they're both כהנים, kohanim, now of course if they're both כהנים, kohanim.
the only way she legitimately married the other guy because if she
didn't legitimately marry he would be a חלל, chalal, right? If she
was a גרושה grusha? then he'd be a חלל. chalal. So if
you want him to be a כהן Kohen, on either side, the
only real scenario is that כהן Kohen. number one died. Okay. So
they're both כהנים. Kohanim, So he's definitely a כהן. Kohen. So what's
at stake? So היו שניהם כהנים. hayu sheneihem kohanim. הוא אונן עליהם.
hu onen aleihem. If either of his fathers dies, he's an אונן.
onen. Now an אונן onen does not mean he's מטמא. It means
that he's not allowed to eat, either way if he's a כהן
Kohen, on either side he works in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
But if a person is an אונן onen and he doesn't work
in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. An אונן onen is the day
that the immediate relative died. So when one of the potential fathers
dies מספק mi-safek he's מחמיר machmir and he assumes he's an אונן.
onen. והם אוננים עליו, ve-hem onenim alav, similarly if he dies, both
of them have to be מחמיר machmir and assume that their son
died and they're אוננים onanim and can't do the עבודה avodah in
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. הוא אינו מטמא להם, hu eino mitamei
lahem, if one of them, however if one of them dies, he's
not allowed to become טמא because it might not be his father.
והם אין מטמאים לו, ve-hem ein mitama-im lo, and similarly if he
dies, they can't become טמא to him because he might not be
their son. הוא אינו יורש אותן, hu eino yoresh otan, he doesn't
inherit them because the other heirs say to him, prove you're the
son. And since you can't prove that you're the son we're not
giving you any part of the inheritance.
והם יורשים אותו, ve-hem yorshim oto, but if he dies and he
has no children, so then the father gets it. So these two
say look, between us one of them is the father, let's just
split it, right? Nobody else has a rightful claim to us, one
of us definitely has a rightful claim to his estate if he
has no kids. Right? So they're going to, so the two potential
fathers are going to split it.
And the inheritance, המוציא מחברו ha-motzi me-chavero was on him. Right. ופטור
על מכתם ועל קללתם של זה ושל
זה,
u-patur al makatam ve-al kilelatam shel
zeh
ve-shel zeh,
if he smites or curses one of his fathers, one of his
potential fathers, he's exempt because you don't know that it was the
real father. What if he hits them both at once, you know?
Or curses them both at once? Anyway. עולה במשמרו של זה ושל
זה. oleh be-mishmaro shel zeh ve-shel zeh. Now, when it's time to
do the עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, if they
come from different families, from different משמרות, mishmarot, he has the right
to do the עבודה avodah on when it's each family's turn. However,
ואינו חולק, ve-eino cholek, he doesn't get a portion in the קרבנות.
korbanos. Because when it comes to the עבודה, avodah, nobody's going to
stop you doing the עבודה, avodah, this might be your turn. If
you want to work, gezuntheit, we'll put you to work. But if
you want to get a portion of the קרבנות, korbanos, you can't
prove that this week is your week.
And if you can't prove it's your week, we're not going to
give you a portion of the קרבנות. korbanos. ואם היו שניהם במשמר
אחד, ve-im hayu sheneihem be-mishmar echad, if it happened that both fathers
were from the same משמר, mishmar, then נוטל חלק אחד, notel chelek
echad,
then he can get, he not only works that week but he's
given a portion. Not two portions, he only has one father. Yes.
When it was כהן וישראל, Kohen ve-Yisrael, when it was one and
one, yeah, does that pass down like forever indefinitely?
Oh, the ספק, safek, yeah, the ספק safek gets continued. Right.
Their descendants can
never...
His kids would always be, I mean, he could always, if he
actually went out and married a גרושה, grusha. then he made his
kids totally חללים. challalim. But yes, that's a good point, the ספק
safek would continue, yes.
How would you figure out if he was the only ספק כהן
safek Kohen in שול shul he'd get an עליה?
aliyah? Good question. Alright, moving on. גופא, Gufa, נכנס לחליצה ואחר כך
יבום, Nichnas l'chalitza ve'achar kach yibbum, so going to the case by
the way about about the יבום yibbum case, about not knowing who
the father is and one doing חליצה chalitza and one doing יבום.
yibbum. So like we said, one guy has to do חליצה chalitza
first and then יבום, yibbum, או יבום ברישא? o yibbum be'reisha? No,
but you can't do יבום yibbum first because דפגע ביבמה לשוק, de'paga
b'yevamah l'shuk, שמא shema it might not be the sister-in-law and then
he's having sex with a woman who still requires חליצה. chalitza. Okay,
אמר שמואל: Amar Shmuel: עשרה כהנים עומדים ופירש אחד מהן ובעל. Asarah
Kohanim omdim u'peirash echad meihen u'va'al. You have ten Kohanim and one
of them and you don't know who went and had sex with
a woman. והולד שתוקי. Ve'havalad shtuki. The kid is a שתוקי. shtuki.
שתוקי Shtuki is like a kid who you don't know who the
father is, right? He says "Who's my daddy?" and you say "Shut
up." So anyway, so that's שתוקי. shtuki. So, מאי שתוקי? Mai shtuki?
Now for what halachic, why do we care halachically, meaning you know
he's a כהן, Kohen, so what difference does it make that you
don't know exactly who his father, I mean, it has a נפקא
מינה nafka mina for like inheritance, but שתוקי shtuki sounds like it's
something much more than inheritance, about personal status. What difference does it
make? You know that he's a total כהן, Kohen. you just don't
know who his father is.
אילימא דמשתקינן ליה מנכסי דאביו? Ilima d'mashtakinan lei minechasei d'aviv? So if
it's just that he doesn't get an inheritance, פשיטא, pishita, of course
not. מי ידעינן אבוה מנו? Mi yad'inan avuh manu? Of course we
don't know who the father is, so you don't need שמואל Shmuel
to tell it to me. And again, שתוקי shtuki sounds like it's
more than just not inheriting, it sounds like a real personal status
issue.
אלא דמשתקינן ליה מדיני כהונה. Ela d'mashtakinan lei midinei kehunah. He's deprived
of some of the privileges of being a כהן. Kohen We'll see
what it means specifically is he's not allowed to work in the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, even though you know he's a כהן. Kohen.
Why not? מאי טעמא? אמר קרא: Amar kra: והייתה לו ולזרעו אחריו
ברית כהונת עולם. V'hayesa lo u'l'zaro acharav bris kehunas olam. To him
and to his seed after him a covenant of priesthood. בעינן זרעו
מיוחס אחריו. Ba'inan zaro meyuchas acharav. Only somebody who knows who his
father is. You need זרעו אחריו, zaro acharav, the seed after him.
You need to know what the, what the, you know, sort of
genealogy is, who the father is
in order to be entitled to work in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. וליכא. Ve'leika. You don't have it. מתקיף לה רב פפא? Matkif
lah Rav Pappa? So רב פפא asked on this. אלא מעתה גבי
אברהם דכתיב להיות לך לאלהים ולזרעך אחריך. Ela mei'atah gabei Avraham de'chsiv
lihayos lach l'Elohim u'l'zaracha acharecha. התם מאי קא מזהיר ליה רחמנא? Hasam
mai ka maz'hir lei Rachmana? What is God telling Abraham? Does that
mean that if some ישראל Yisrael doesn't know who his father is,
he's somehow excluded from the people, excluded from God? We would never
say that.
הכי קאמר ליה: Hachi ka'amar lei: לא תנסב עובדת כוכבים ושפחה דלא
ליזיל זרעך בתרה. Lo tinsav ovedes kochavim u'shifchah d'lo leizil zaracha basrah.
No, means זרעך אחריך, zaracha acharecha, he's telling Abraham marry a woman
whose kids will be Jewish. Don't marry a non-Jewish woman or a
slave woman and then it won't be זרעך אחריך. zaracha acharecha. Okay,
but that's what God's telling Abraham, keep in the faith. But by
כהנים, it's telling something more, you have to know who your father
is to be entitled to work in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. מיתיבי, Meisivei, one minute, that doesn't... I'll ask
you on this. ראשון ראוי להיות כהן גדול. Rishon ra'ui lihayos Kohen
Gadol. We had this discussion before about a woman who
didn't know, again, had יבום yibbum within three months. So the brother,
you know, it was a case of a כהן, kohen. and the
brother obviously was a כהן, kohen and we don't know again who
the father is, just like this case. And it said that even
though you don't know who the father is, he could be a
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the kid. Doesn't matter, you know that he's
a כהן. kohen, So that's a pretty good proof against שמואל. Shmuel.
והא בעינן זרע מיוחס אחריו וליכא? Ve'ha ba'inan zera meyuchas acharav v'leika?
You don't have this
זרע מיוחס אחריו. zera meyuchas acharav. זרע מיוחס אחריו דרבנן וקרא אסמכתא
בעלמא. Zera meyuchas acharav derabbanan u'kra asmachta be'alma. Fine, you're right, whatever,
that whole idea was rabbinic. It's only rabbinic. Okay, it's rabbinic, but
why do we say he could be a
כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? וכי גזור רבנן בזנות? Ve'chi gazar rabbanan biznus?
And therefore, when שמואל Shmuel said that we're going to give them
a disqualified status, that was not a case of a legitimate marriage,
you just don't know whether he was, you know, whether it was
the first husband or the second husband, there we would not disqualify
him. We're talking about a case where this כהן kohen? just out
of marriage slept with a woman. This woman slept with some man,
she doesn't know who the man was, she knows he was a
כהן. That case, because it was an issue of זנות, znus, there
it sort of makes a much more problematic status for the child,
and you understand it a little bit, right? A person who doesn't
know who his father is because his mother was randomly, was sleeping
with some random man is seen as, you know, obviously the whole
idea of personal status and societal status and whatever, that's much more
deeply problematic as a sense of, you know, your societal standing as
opposed to somebody whose mother was, you know, was legitimately married to
husband one, legitimately married to husband number two, she just doesn't know,
you know, which one, but she didn't do anything wrong, there was
no זנות znus involved. That doesn't affect the standing. Okay, so כי
גזור רבנן בזנות. ki gazar rabbanan biznus. בנישואין לא גזור רבנן. Be'nisu'in
lo gazar rabbanan. So now the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, ובזנות
מי גזור רבנן? u'viznus mi gazar rabbanan? Is that really true?
והתנן, Ve'hatnan, let's look at our case in our משנה. Mishnah. מי
שלא שהתה אחר בעלה שלושה חודשים ונישאת וילדה. Mi she'lo shahasa achar
ba'alah shloshah chodashim ve'nisas ve'yaldah. So a woman didn't wait after her
husband, she remarried, and she gave birth. מאי אחר בעלה? Mai achar
ba'alah? So she didn't wait after her husband. What happened to husband
number one in our משנה? Mishnah?
אילימא אחר מיתת בעלה, ileima achar misas ba'ala, the husband number one
died? אימא סיפא, eima seifa, can't be died because we say in
the end, הוא אונן עליהם והם אינם אוננים עליו, hu onen aleihem
vehem einan onenim alav, that he is an אונן onen when they
die and they're אונן onen when he dies. So it sounds like
both of his fathers are alive, right? 'Cause it says they will
be an אונן onen if he dies, he will be an אונן
onen if either one of them dies. So it sounds like they're
all alive. So can't be the father number one died. בשלמא הוא
אונן עליהם, bishlama hu onen aleihem, he could be an אונן onen
on them even if one had already died. How could he be
a new אונן onen on him? משכחת לה בנישואין דשני וליקוט עצמות
דקמא. meshkachas la benisuin desheni velikut atzamos dekama. The second one, you
know, that he's בנישואין, benisuin, you have it through a case of
נישואין nisuin because for the second and the first guy because of
ליקוט עצמות, likut atzamos, which basically means is that you could have
it that they're both alive, I mean, excuse me, the first guy
died, but you could be an אונן onen on him when you
rebury the bones, reinter the bones. So we could have a case
where the first guy died and she legitimately married the second husband
and wasn't a גרושה grusha. case, it was an אלמנה almana case.
And nevertheless, he could be an אונן onen on the first guy
again because of a reinterment after the נישואין דשני.
nisuin desheni. Right.
אלא הם אוננים עליו היכי משכחת לה? ela hem onenim alav heichi
meshkachas la? How do you have that either one can be an
אונן onen on him? It means that they're both alive. קמא המית
ליה, kama hamis lei, the first guy already died. So if we're
talking about both fathers being alive, how did this woman remarry? דלאו
בגרושה? delav begrusha? Must be she was divorced from guy number one.
But then if ומה אחר בעלה, umai achar ba'ala, so what does
it mean she didn't wait after her husband? It means אחר גט
בעלה, achar get ba'ala, after she was divorced. Okay. So it's a
good, right? It's very clear. The משנה Mishnah makes it sound very
clearly both fathers are alive. Here this woman remarried to a כהן.
So presumably she remarried, she's a גרושה though. Okay. אימא סיפא. eima
seifa. הוא אינו מיטמא להם והם אינם מיטמאים לו. hu eino mitamei
lahem vehem einam mitam'im lo. He doesn't become טמא to them, them
not to him. בשלמא הם אינם מיטמאים לו לחומרא, bishlama hem einam
mitam'im lo lechumra, they don't become טמא to him
לחומרא, lechumra, דכל חד וחד דאמר לאו בריה הוא, dekol chad vechad
de'amar lav berei hu, because each father says he might not be
my son. אלא הוא אינו מיטמא להם, ela hu eino mitamei lahem,
but he, why can't he be מיטמא mitamei to them? אמאי? amai?
Why? בשלמא לשני לא ליטמי ליה, bishlama lesheni lo litemei lei, he
doesn't become טמא to the second father, because maybe he's the son
of the first father and this guy isn't his father. אבל אלא
לראשון ליטמי ליה ממה נפשך, aval ela lerishon litemei lei mima nafshach,
but why shouldn't he be מיטמא mitamei to the first father? אי
בריה הוא, ei berei hu, if he's the son of the first
father, שפיר קמיטמי ליה, shapir kamitamei lei, it's good, he should be
מיטמא mitamei to him. ואי בר בתרא הוא, ve'ei bar basra hu,
and if he's the son of the second one,
שפיר קמיטמי ליה לראשון. shapir kamitamei lei lerishon. Why? דחלל הוא, dechalal
hu, because he's a חלל, chalal, right? If these are both כוהנים
kohanim and she was divorced and she's a גרושה, so the possibility
they come from here would make him a חלל. chalal. So he's
only a good כהן if he came from number one. So if
father number one died, he said, look, I can become מיטמא mitamei
to you ממה נפשך. mima nafshach. Either you're my father and I'm
a good כהן, or I'm from this union and I'm a חלל
chalal and I can also be מיטמא mitamei to you. So how
do you deal with this whole case? How do you have a
case where both fathers are alive and he's definitely a kosher כהן?
It's a good question, it's a little riddle. So let's see what
the גמרא answer is. אלא
לאו,
ela
lav, so the גמרא says בזנות. biznus. It must be that no,
there was no marriage to the first guy. Yes, you might be
the first guy's son, but they were never married. So then she
went ahead and she just married the second guy. Got it? So
they were never married, she's not a גרושה, she's not an אלמנה.
almana. Okay, but she might be one of their sons, he's not
a חלל chalal because she's not a גרושה. And that's the scenario
that they're both alive and he might be the legitimate son of
either one of them. Not אנוסה, anusa, we're saying זנות. znus. Don't
you introduce אנוסה. anusa. Okay, so anyway, so that's the scenario. Okay,
that's the scenario. But now what do you have? You have this
guy who doesn't know who his father was and he was conceived
בזנות. biznus. And he can work in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
So that's a proof against שמואל. Shmuel. That's a pretty good way
to go, הדר תרצא. hadar tirtza. Okay. ומה אחר בעלה? umai achar
ba'ala? What does it mean she married the second guy after the
husband she went to the second guy? אחר בועלה, achar bo'ala, after
the guy she's been sleeping with. ותני סיפא vesani seifa עולה במשמר
של זה ושל זה, ola bemishmar shel zeh veshel zeh, that he
can go ahead and work in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So
the only way to read the משנה Mishnah is that he wasn't
married to guy number one, so both fathers are alive and she's
not a גרושה and he can work in the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. תיובתא דשמואל, tiuvta deShmuel, it's a contradiction to שמואל. Shmuel. Okay,
so let's just read one answer.
אמר רב שמעיה בממאנת. amar Rav Shemaya bemema'enes. No, we're talking about
a case of בממאנת, bemema'enes, meaning she could have been married to
him, but she, he's not the child of a זנות. znus. How
does she get freed from husband one and husband one's alive and
she's not a גרושה? She was married to him when she was
a minor, and she was married off by the fathers and the
brothers, and then she does מיאון. miun. And then she does מיאון,
miun, so she walks away without a גט, get, but it was
a legitimate, it wasn't זנות, znus, it was a rabbinically sanctioned
marriage. The גמרא says, ואם אנוס מעיקרא ילדה. veim anus meikara yalda.
One minute. If she was a ממאנת mema'enes she wouldn't have had
a kid. Exactly.
דתני רב ביבי
Datani Rav Bibi because she's underage. But רב ביבי קמיה
דרב נחמן, Rav Bibi kamie d'Rav Nachman, שלש נשים משמשות במוך—we shalosh
nashim meshamshos bemoch had this before, I'm not redoing this—three women are
allowed to use a form of like a sponge, a birth
control: קטנה ומעוברת ומניקה—minor, ktana umeuveres umenika pregnant, and nursing. קטנה שמא
תתעבר ותמות—a ktana shema tisaver vesamus minor because if she gets pregnant
she'll it'll kill her. מעוברת שמא תעשה עוברה סנדל—a meuveres shema taaseh
ubarah sandal pregnant woman because if she gets pregnant again or what
if she have sex or whatever it'll affect the fetus.
ומניקה שמא תגמול את בנה וימות—and umenika shema sigmol es benah veyamus
a nursing woman because if she has another child she'll have to
wean the first child. ואיזו היא קטנה? veizo hi ktana? And what's
a minor? מבת אחת עשרה שנה ויום אחד עד בת שתים עשרה
שנה ויום אחד—from mibas achas esre shana veyom echad ad bas shtaim
esre shana veyom echad eleven till twelve. פחות מכאן—if pachos mikan it's
less than eleven she won't get pregnant. או יתר—or o yeser more
then she won't it won't be a risk to life. משמשת כדרכה
והולכת—she meshamashesh kedarka veholeches can go ahead and have sex without a
birth control. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. וחכמים אומרים אחת זו
ואחת זו משמשת כדרכה והולכת—either vachachamim omrim achas zu veachas zu meshamashesh
kedarka veholeches way she can or she must not use birth control.
ומן השמים ירחמו—and umin hashamayim yerachamu they'll have compassion from heaven, שנאמר
שומר פתאים ה׳. shenemar shomer pesayim Hashem. So what do you see?
You see that if she's under twelve and she gets pregnant she
won't survive. She'll die! So you can't have a scenario that she
was a ממאנת mema'enes that she was married under age and had
a kid. So the גמרא says, okay, משתכח לה בקידושי טעות. mishtakcha
lah bekidushi taus. Fine. The scenario is not ממאנת, mema'enes, she was
married to number one and had a kid and then it turned
out that the whole thing was a mistake. קידושי טעות. kidushi taus.
You know, there was some deception or whatever he had married her
based on some assumptions, the assumptions turned out to be false, and
therefore the marriage was dissolved, but the kid was born in the
context of a marriage and therefore the kid is not born בזנות
biznus and therefore she's free without being a גרושה. Okay. וכהא דאמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, vechiha deamar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, דאמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל משום רבי ישמעאל: deamar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel mishum
Rabbi Yishmael: ואילו לא נתפשה אסורה—the veilu lo nispsha asura woman wasn't
raped she's forbidden to her husband. הנתפשה
מותרת—if hanispsha muteres she was raped she's permissible. ויש לך אחרת—you veyesh
lach acheres have another woman שאף על פי שלא נתפשה—even sheaf al
pi shelo nispsha if she sleeps with some man and she wasn't
raped, מותרת—she's muteres allowed. ואיזו זו? veizo zu? קדושי קדושי טעות. kidushi
kidushi taus.
This is a woman that was married, so she was legitimately married
to a man, but then it turned out that it wasn't married
to because it was all a טעות. taus. שאפילו בנה מורכב על
כתיפה—that sheafilu benah murkav al kesefah even if the child is now
on her on her shoulders, ממאנת והולכת לה—she mema'enes veholeches lah walks
away from the marriage. So when it was a קידושי טעות, kidushi
taus, when there was a real error in the marriage, then she
just walks away, the marriage is dissolved. So both husbands could be
alive and she could have a child and she's not a גרושה.
And therefore it's possible to still maintain שמואל's Shmuel contention that a
child born בזנות biznus with a question who the father is, is
not entitled to work in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Okay,
there we go.
Wait a minute. We don't do
that.